A Guide to the Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-1964: SC 0132
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection,
1896-1964
Special Collections, James Madison University
Sons of Confederate Veterans
SC 0132
.4 cubic feet; 1 box
The Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-1964, consists of documents pertaining to the Sons of Confederate Veterans (SCV) organization at the local, state, and national levels.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Other Formats Available
This collection is also available on Microfilm #1487 and may be used instead of the originals. The microfilm is available in Special Collections.
Administrative History
The SCV is a national fraternal organization established in 1895 for veterans of the Confederate forces and their sons and grandsons, with chapters around the nation.
Scope and Content
The Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-1964, consists of documents pertaining to the Sons of Confederate Veterans (SCV) organization at the local, state, and national levels. The papers include letters from the national and state headquarters, many documents from the Harrisonburg SCV, applications for membership in the Harrisonburg SCV, and documents from other camps in Virginia located outside of Rockingham County.
Series 1: National Headquarters Documents, 1912-1964, contains papers which were sent from the main offices of the SCV in Richmond, Virginia. These papers consist of convention notices, dues requests and general orders for all chapters, nationwide.
Series 2: State Headquarters Documents, 1898-1940, is comprised of papers originating in the Virginia Division Headquarters of the SCV in Charlottesville, Va. Once again, the papers are for the most part notices for state conventions and reunions, dues notices and general orders on the state level.
Series 3: D. H. Lee Martz Camp 10, Harrisonburg, 1922-1938, is comprised of documents pertaining to the local camp of the SCV. The series includes membership rosters, dues records, minutes of meetings, letters and various papers all having to do with the maintenance of an active camp of the SCV. Also of interest are a few examples of Apple Blossom Festival stationery.
Series 4: Applications, 1896-1927, contains applications in various forms for membership in Camp 10 and other camps. Included in some of these applications are records of Southern veterans with their rank, company, number of years served, and reason for discharge from the Confederate army.
Series 5: Camps outside Rockingham County, 1899-1923, is comprised mostly of annual reports of camps in Virginia for 1923. Included as well are a few miscellaneous papers from some of the camps. Of particular note is a printed pamphlet "Charter, By-laws, Rules of Order and List of Officers and Members of RE Lee Camp, No. 1...1884."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series 1: National Headquarters Documents, 1912-1964
Series 2: State Headquarters Documents, 1898-1940
Series 3: D. H. Lee Martz Camp 10, Harrisonburg, 1922-1938
Series 4: Applications, 1896-1927
Series 5: Camps outside Rockingham County, 1899-1923
Index Terms
Subjects:
Sons of Confederate Veterans (Organization) -- Records and correspondence; Sons of Confederate Veterans (Organization). D. H. Lee Martz Camp (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Records and correspondence; Confederate States of America -- History -- Societies, etc.; Confederate States of America. Army -- Biography; Confederate States of America -- History, Military -- Sources; Martz family -- Sources; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Sources; United States -- Armed Forces -- Biography; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Societies, etc. -- Confederate; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources
- Series 1: National Headquarters Documents, 1912-1964
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1912-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2: State Headquarters Documents, 1898-1940
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1898-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 3: D.H. Lee Martz Camp 10, Harrisonburg, 1922-1938
  - Membership Rosters and Dues Records, 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, By-laws, 1922-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, Business Papers, 1923-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Applications for Membership in SCV Camps, 1896-1927; Series 4
  - Applications, 1896-1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Applications, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 5: Camps outside Rockingham County, 1899-1923
  - Documents of Camps #1-14, 204, 1899-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)